A Guide to the Papers of Carleton Sprague 1904-1905
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Carleton Sprague 1904-1905
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11193
The collection consists of 11 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains two letters, 1905 April 18 and May 29, from Richard Watson Gilder, thanking Sprague for a letter and discussing an ode he is writing; a letter, 1905 November 11, from Charles M. Kurtz requesting permission to reprint in a publication; a printed memorial to President McKinley; four poems; a copyright certificate from the Library of Congress, and two cabinet photographs by the London photographer Frederick Hollyer.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Printed Memorial Poem, "J.G.M." by Carleton Sprague (1858-1916) 1904 Jan, 1 p., printed
  - Printed Christmas Poem, beginning "Ah, yes, 'tis Christmas! 'Tis the holy morn" by Carleton Sprague sent to Bryant B. [Gilhenny?], Jr. 1910, 1 p., printed
  - Poem "to A.B.S." [Alice Brayley Sprague] by Carleton Sprague, with a single penned correction 1911 Apr 17, 1 p., with envelope, TMsS
  - Untitled brief autograph poem written on a blank card sent by Carleton Sprague probably to Alice Sprague and accompanying a gift of flowers n.d., 1 p., AMsS
- Letters
  - Richard Watson Gilder (1844-1909), Fair Brooks Farm, to Carleton Sprague [1903 Sep?] 18, 1 p., ALS
    [writing from his sick bed, he assures Sprague that he has the matter in mind and "not without hopes" promising to let him know in time to respond with a "more serviceable muse." He also notes that the opening will probably be in June]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, Editorial Department, The Century Magazine, New York City, to Carleton Sprague, Buffalo, New York 1905 May 29, 1 p., TLS
    [writes concerning one of his poems, "My muse has played a trick on me, as is the way of muses, and I have inserted in my ode a new strophe which will be the fifth--just before the close. It might be well if the Buffalo papers had it right and in full. As for the others, they have more of the ode than they are likely to print, anyhow. I called a poet friend of mine yesterday into consultation after writing this fifth strophe and he thought that it added weight and value to the ode (supposing the ode to have any weight or value!)"]
  - Director Charles M. Kurtz (1855-1909), The Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, Albright Art Gallery, Buffalo, New York, to Carleton Sprague 1905 Nov 11, 2 p. on 2 l., ALS
    [thanks Sprague for the copy of The Mission of Beauty, "You have charmingly voiced feelings which are shared by many, but which rarely - if ever before - have been expressed so intimately and impressively," and asks permission to use a few extracts in a forthcoming issue of National Academy Notes, some of which he cites in the letter]
- Photographs
  - Two sepia cabinet photographs of Carleton Sprague by the noted London photographer, Frederick Hollyer; a profile photograph and one with Sprague leaning his head onto his hand n.d., sepia
- Printed
  - A printed memorial to President William McKinley following his assassination on September 6, 1901, at a meeting of The Saturn Club, Buffalo 1901 Sep 21, 4 p., printed
- Miscellaneous
  - Library of Congress copyright form filled out by Carleton Sprague for his The Mission of Beauty. A Poem. published by the Matthews-Northrup Works, Buffalo, New York 1905 Nov 3, printed form